Time to get up, man.
该起床了
- All right, Dad.    - Come on.
- 好的，老爸    - 快点
Should be here soon.
马上来了
- I think I should make a list.    - What do mean?
- 我想我该列个表    - 干嘛？
- For your birthday gifts?    - Yeah.
- 想要的生日礼物？    - 对呀
You know you're only getting a couple of things, right?
你知道只能要几个礼物，对吧？
Yeah, I know. Just to look at and study so I can choose better.
知道啊，我只想列出来看看 研究一下，好好选选
Okay, well, that's smart. Yeah, make a list.
哦，很聪明，那就列吧
Can you spell everything you're thinking of?
想要的礼物你都会写吗？
- I think so.    - All right. That's good.
- 应该吧    - 哦，很好
- How you doing in here, man?    - Okay.
- 小伙子，你还好吧？    - 还好
Can we go to the park today, after?
我们今天能去公园吗… 在上完幼儿园后？
No, I gotta go to Oakland. Well, maybe, we'll see.
呃…我还得去奥克兰 或许…再说吧
Give me a kiss.
亲亲
I'll talk to you later.
晚点再说
Excuse me.
借过
Oh, excuse me...
对不起…呃…
...when is somebody gonna clean this off?
什么时候会找人清洗一下？
And the Y? The Y. We talked about this.
我提过的，幸福的“幸”写错了
It's an I in "happiness." There's no Y in "happiness." It's an I.
这里写成了辛苦的“辛”
I'm Chris Gardner.
我是克里斯・迦纳
I met my father for the first time when I was 28 years old.
我第一次见到我父亲时，已经28岁了
And I made up my mind as a young kid...
我儿时就决定，将来我有了孩子
...my children were gonna know who their father was.
我的孩子一定得知道他们的父亲是谁
This is part of my life story.
这里讲述的是我人生故事的一部分
This part is called "Riding the Bus."
这部分叫做…“搭公车”
What's that?
那是什么？
It's a time machine, isn't it?
是架时光机，对吧？
Seems like a time machine.
看起来是时光机
That seems like a time machine. It's a time machine. Take me with you.
像是时光机，是时光机，能带上我吗？
This machine...
这仪器…
...this machine on my lap...
我膝盖上的这台仪器…
This guy, he has a time machine.
这伙计，他有架时光机
He travels in the past with this machine and...
他…他…他…用时光机穿梭到过去
- it is not a time machine.
这不是…时光机
It' a portable bone-density scanner.
而是，手提式骨质密度扫描仪
A medical device I sell for a living.
是医疗器材，我就靠卖这个过活
Thank you for the opportunity to discuss it with you.
谢谢您给我这个机会，向您推介这仪器
- I appreciate it.    - We just don't need it, Chris.
- 我不胜感激    -  我们真的不需要，克里斯
It's unnecessary and expensive.
没多大用处而且还很贵
- Well, maybe next...    - Thank you.
- 哦，或许下次…    - 谢谢
It gave a slightly denser picture than an x-ray for twice the money.
它比X光机显像更精确一点点 但却贵了一倍
- Hey.    - Hey, baby.
- 嘿    - 嘿，宝贝
- What happened?    - No, nothing.
- 怎么啦？    - 没…没事儿
Look, I can't get Christopher today.
只是…我今天不能去接儿子
Oh, no, you don't, Chris. I'm back on at 7.
你得去，我七点还要上班
I know. I have got to go to Oakland.
我知道，但我一定要去奥克兰
So I gotta get Christopher home, feed him, bathe him...
所以我得先接他回家，做饭，给他洗澡…
...get him in bed, and be back here by 7?
哄他睡觉，然后七点前回到这儿？
- Yes.    - And we got the tax-bill notice today.
- 对    - 今天收到了税单
- What are you gonna do about that?    - Look, this is what we gotta do.
- 你说怎么办？    - 听着，就这么办
You see that car? The one with the pretty yellow shoe on it?
看到那车了吗？ 那辆穿着漂亮黄鞋子的车
That' mine.
那是我的车
There' no parking near hospitals.
医院附近不准停车
That' what happens when you're always in a rush.
赶时间的结果就是这样
Thanks anyway. Very much.
还是非常谢谢你
- Maybe next quarter.    - It's possible.
- 或许下个季度    - 可能哦
I needed to sell at least two scanners a month for rent and daycare.
我每个月至少得卖两台 才够付房租和幼儿园费
I'd have to sell one more...
还得再卖一台…
...to pay off all of those tickets under my windshield wiper.
才够付车窗上的那些罚单
The problem is...
问题是…
...I haven't sold any for a while.
我很久没卖出一台了
Since when do you not like macaroni and cheese?
你什么时候开始不喜欢通心粉加奶酪的？
Since birth?
从…我出生开始？
- What's that?    - What?
- 这是什么？    - 呃？
- What is this?    - It's a gift for Christopher.
- 这是什么东西？    - 克里斯托弗的礼物
- From who?    - Cynthia from work.
- 谁给的？    - 我同事欣西雅
It's for adults. Chris can't use it. She didn't know.
她不知道这是给大人玩的，克里斯托弗还小
What are you supposed to do with it?
要怎么玩？
Make every side the same color.
把每一面都弄成同一颜色
Did you pay the taxes?
你付税了吗？
No, I'm gonna have to file an extension.
没，我要申请延后缴
- You already filed an extension.    - Yeah, well, I gotta file another one.
- 你已经申请过延期了    - 是，我还要再延期一次
That's... It's $650. I'll have it in the next month.
一共是640美元，我下个月就有了
That means interest, right?
- 是加上利息，还有罚金的总额吧    - 嗯，不是很多啦
Look, why don't you let me do this? All right, just relax. Okay?
让我处理就好 你就别操心了，好吗？
- Come here. Calm down.    - I have to go back to work.
- 来，别烦了    - 我得回去工作了
Let's get ready for bed. Hey, put your plate in the sink.
准备上床了 嗨，把盘子放水池里去
A few days ago I was presented with a report I'd asked for...
几天前他们递交了一份 我要求的…
...a comprehensive audit, if you will, of our economic condition.
全面的经济现况评估报告
You won't like it. I didn't like it.
你们不会喜欢的，我也不喜欢
But we have to face the truth...
但我们必须面对现实
...and then go to work to turn things around.
然后去努力扭转情势
And make no mistake about it, we can turn them around.
决不能犯错，我们一定能做到
The federal budget is out of control.
联邦预算已经失去控制
And we face runaway deficits of almost $80 billion...
今年9月30日结束的预算年度
...for this budget year that ends September 30th.
我们将有高达800亿的赤字
That deficit is larger than the entire federal budget in 1957.
这个赤字比1957年整年联邦预算还高
And so is the almost $80 billion...
今年还得支付这800亿…
...we will pay in interest this year on the national debt.
…衍生的利息国债
Twenty years ago, in 1960...
20年前，1960年
...our federal government payroll was less than $ 13 billion.
联邦政府的总薪资支出不到130亿
Today it is 75 billion.
而如今则是750亿
During these 20 years, our population has only increased by 23.3 percent...
20年来人口才增长了23.3%…
Man, I got two questions for you:
哇，老兄，请教你两个问题
What do you do? And how do you do it?
你是干什么？ 你是怎么干的？
- I'm a stockbroker.    - Stockbroker. Oh, goodness.
- 我是股票经纪人    - 股票经纪人，哦，天哪
Had to go to college to be a stockbroker, huh?
得上大学才能做股票经纪人，对吧？
You don't have to. Have to be good with numbers and good with people.
不用，只需要精通数字，会做人处世
- That's it.    - Hey, you take care.
- 就这么简单    - 嘿，保重
I'll let you hang on to my car for the weekend.
周末我这车就借你了
- But I need it back for Monday.    - Feed the meter.
- 不过星期一得还我哦    - 付停车费去吧
I still remember that moment.
我还记得那一刻
They all looked so damn happy to me.
他们全都看起来 超幸福的样子
Why couldn't I look like that?
为什么我不能也满脸幸福？
I'm gonna try to get home by 6.
我尽量在六点前回来
I'm gonna stop by a brokerage firm after work.
下班后要去一下证券行
- For what?    - I wanna see about a job there.
- 干嘛？    - 看看那里有没有工作
Yeah? What job?
哦，什么样的工作？
You know, when l...
你知道，我…
When I was a kid, I could go through a math book in a week.
我小时候，一星期就能把算数课本念完
So I'm gonna go see about what job they got down there.
所以我想去看看，有什么工作可做
What job?
什么工作？
Stockbroker.
股票经纪人
- Stockbroker?    - Yeah.
- 股票经纪人？    - 嗯
Not an astronaut?
不是宇航员？
Don't talk to me like that, Linda.
别用这种口气对我说话，琳达
I'm gonna go down and see about this, and I'm gonna do it during the day.
我去看看情况，利用白天的时间
You should probably do your sales calls.
嗯，你该打电话推销才对
I don't need you to tell me about my sales calls, Linda.
还要你来告诉我，琳达
I got three of them before the damn office is even open.
人家办公室开门前，我就打了三通电话了
Do you remember that rent is due next week?
还记得下星期就要付房租吗？
Probably not.
大概不记得了吧？
We're already two months behind.
我们已经两个月没付
Next week we'll owe three months.
下星期就欠三个月了
I've been pulling double shifts for four months now, Chris.
我已经上双份班四个月了！
Just sell what's in your contract. Get us out of that business.
就…赶快把合约规定的数额卖完 咱们好脱身吧
Linda, that is what I am trying to do.
琳达，我不是正努力那么做嘛！
This is what I'm trying to do for my family...
努力来改善这个家
...for you and for Christopher.
为你，为儿子
What's the matter with you?
你到底是怎么了？
Linda.
琳达
This part of my life is called "Being Stupid."
我人生的这部分 叫做…“冒傻气”
Can I ask you a favor, miss?
能帮个忙吗，小姐
Do you mind if I leave this here with you just for five minutes?
帮我看下这个行吗，就5分钟
I have a meeting in there and I don't wanna carry that...
我在那儿有个会 带这个进去看上去很不正式
Here is a dollar and I'll give you more money when I come back out.
先给你1块钱 一会我出来再多给你点
Okay? It's not valuable. You can't sell it anywhere.
好吗？ 这玩意不值钱，你也卖不出去
I can't even sell it, and it's my job. All right?
我是干这个的都卖不掉，好吗？
- Chris? Tim Brophy, Resources.    - Yes. How are you?
- 克里斯吗？我是提姆・布鲁菲，人事部的    - 是我，你好吗？
- Come with me.    - Yes, sir.
- 跟我来    - 好的，先生
Let me see if I can find you an application for our internship.
我看看能不能帮你找份实习申请表
I'm afraid that's all we can do for you. See, this is a satellite office.
我能做的也只有这个了 这里只是分公司
Jay Twistle in the main office, he oversees Witter Resources.
总部的杰・托斯特尔是 全面负责人事工作的
I mean, I'm... You know, I'm just this office.
我的意思是，我只负责这里
As you can see, we got a hell of lot of applications here, so...
你看，已经有一大堆人申请了 …所以…
Normally I have a resume sheet, but I can't seem to find it anywhere.
我这应该还有履历表的 但是现在找不到了
- We...    - Thank you very much.
- 我们…    - 非常感谢
I need to go.
我得走了
I'll bring this back.
我…我…我会把这个交过来的
- Thank you.    - Okay.
- 谢谢    - 好的
Trusting a hippie girl with my scanner. Why did I do that?
把扫描仪托付给一个嬉皮女孩？ 为什么我会这么做？
Excuse me. Excuse me.
借过，借过
Like I said, this part of my life is called "Being Stupid."
就像我刚说的，我人生的这部分 叫做“冒傻气”
Hey! Hey! Hey! Don't move! Don't move! Stay...!
嘿，嘿！ 别动！呆着别动！别…
Stop! Stop!
停下！停下！
Don't move! Stop this...! Stop the train!
别走！停下！停下这地铁！
The program took just 20 people every six months.
这个培训每半年才招20人
One got the job.
最后只有1人受雇
There were three blank lines after "high school" to list more education.
申请表上“高中”之后还有3行线 用来填写接受过的其他教育
I didn't need that many lines.
对我来说，根本就是多余
Try and sleep. It's late.
快睡觉，不早了
It' a puzzle measuring just 3 inches by 3 inches on each side...
这种魔方每面都是3英寸x3英寸
...made up of multiple colors that you twist and turn...
由多种颜色组成 玩法就是通过旋转
...and try to get to a solid color on each side.
最终使每面呈现同一颜色
This little cube is the gift sensation of 1981.
这小玩意是1981年的送礼佳品
Don't expect to solve it easily.
但是想把它玩好可没那么容易
Although we did encounter one math professor at USF...
尽管我们确实碰到一位 旧金山大学的数学教授
...who took just 30 minutes on his.
只花了30分钟就拼好
This is as far as I've gotten on mine.
这个是我尽最大努力拼的了
As you can see, I still have a long way to go.
大家可以看到 离完成还早着呢
This is Jim Finnerty reporting for KJSF in Richmond.
这里是吉米・芬尼迪 从KJSF里士满发回的报道
Hey, wake up.
嘿，醒醒
Eat.
快吃
- Bye, Mom.    - Bye, baby.
- 妈，再见    - 再见，宝贝
- Come back without that, please.    - Oh, yeah, I'm going to.
- 那玩意儿卖了再回来    - 噢，我正有此意
So go ahead, say goodbye to it, because I'm coming back without it.
快点和它道个别 回来可就看不到它了
Goodbye and good riddance.
再见，“可喜的摆脱”
You ain't had to add the "good riddance" part.
后面那部分没必要说的
Bye, Mom.
再见，妈妈！
Bye.
再见
It's written as P-P-Y, but it's supposed to be an I in "happiness."
那里写的是“辛” 但是实际上应该是“幸”
- Is it an adjective?    - No, actually it's a noun.
- 是形容词吗？    - 不是，是个名词
But it's not spelled right.
但是字写错了
- Is "fuck" spelled right?    - Yeah, that's spelled right.
- “操”写对了吗？    - 对，那个写的对
But that's not part of the motto, so you're not supposed to learn that.
但是标语里没这词 所以别学
That's an adult word to show anger and other things.
那词是大人用来表达他们愤怒之类的
- But just don't use that one, okay?    - Okay.
- 别用那词，好吗？    - 好的
What's that say on the back of your bag?
你书包背后写的是什么？
My nickname.
我的绰号
We pick nicknames.
我们选了绰号
- Oh, yeah? What's it say?    - "Hot Rod."
- 噢，你选的是什么？    - “改装高速车”
- Did you have a nickname?    - Yep.
- 你有绰号吗？    - 有啊
- What?    - "Ten-Gallon Head."
- 是什么？    - 无-敌-大-头
- What's that?    - I grew up in Louisiana, near Texas.
- 什么意思？    - 我在德克萨斯州附近的路易斯安那长大
Everybody wears cowboy hats. And a ten-gallors a big hat.
那儿的人都戴牛仔帽 那种“10加仑”牛仔帽 （宽边软顶牛仔帽，因分量重而得名）
I was smart back then, so they called me Ten-Gallon Head.
我小时候很聪明 所以大家都叫我“无-敌-大-头”
- Hoss wears that hat.    - Hoss?
- 霍斯也戴那种牛仔帽    - 霍斯？
Hoss Can'twright on Bonanza.
霍斯・卡特赖特 “伯南扎的牛仔”里面的牛仔
- How do you know Bonanza?    - We watch it at Mrs. Chu's.
- 你从哪知道“伯南扎的牛仔”的？    - 在朱太太家看的
- You watch Bonanza at daycare?    - Yeah.
- 你在幼儿园看“伯南扎的牛仔”？    - 是啊
When? When do you watch it?
是什么时候看的？
- After snack? After your nap?    - After Love Boat.
- 午餐后还是午觉后？    - 看完“爱之船”之后看的
I made my list for my birthday.
我生日礼物列好了
- Yeah, what'd you put on there?    - A basketball or an ant farm.
- 你都写了什么？    - 篮球，或者“蚂蚁农场” （“蚂蚁农场”为一种智趣游戏）
- He says he's been watching TV.    - Oh, little TV for history.
- 他说他一直在看电视    - 是啊，是看了些电视，都是历史片
- Love Boat?    - For history. Navy.
- “爱之船”也是吗？    - 是啊，是关于海军历史的
That's not the Navy.
那可不是海军历史片
I mean, he could watch television at home.
我的意思是，他可以在家看电视
We're paying you $ 150 a month. If he's gonna be sitting around...
我们每月付150块给你 要是他就坐在这儿…
...watching TV all day, we're taking him out of here.
一直看电视的话，我们就带他走
Go pay more at other daycare if you don't like Navy TV.
你要是不喜欢海军片的话 就多花钱去别家幼儿园好了
You late pay anyway. You complain. I complain.
反正你总是晚付钱 你抱怨，我还抱怨呢
Can you at least put the dog upstairs in your room or something?
那能不能把狗带到楼上去？ 关到你房间或什么地方
Bye.
再见
I was waiting for Witter Resource head Jay Twistle...
我在等维特公司 人事部主管杰・托斯特尔
...whose name sounded so delightful, like he'd give me a job and a hug.
他的名字听起来很可爱 就好像他会给我份工作，外加一个拥抱
I just had to show him I was good with numbers and good with people.
而我所要做的，就是让他知道 我精通数字，而且懂得待人之道
- Morning, Mr. Twistle.    - Good morning.
- 早上好，托斯特尔先生    - 早上好
- Mr. Twistle, Chris Gardner.    - Hi.
- 托斯特尔先生，我是克里斯・迦纳    - 你好
I wanted to drop this off personally and make your acquaintance.
我得在你进去之前亲自把这个交给您 和您认识一下
I thought I'd catch you on the way in. I'd love the opportunity to discuss...
希望有机会能和您坐下聊聊
...what may seem like weaknesses on my application.
我申请表上看起来比较薄弱的几点
We'll start with this, and we'll call you if we wanna sit down.
好的，我们要先看下你的申请表，克里斯 需要面试的话会通知你的
- Yes, sir. You have a great day.    - You too.
- 好的，先生，祝您愉快    - 你也是
Hey, yeah, how you doing?
嗨，你好
This is Chris Gardner calling for Dr. Delsey.
我是克里斯・迦纳 找戴尔斯医生
Yeah, I'm running a little late for a sales call.
我要晚一点才能来推销
I was wondering if... Yeah, Osteo National.
能不能…对，国立阿斯提公司
Right. We can still...? Half an hour?
对，我们能不能…半小时后？
Yes. Beautiful. Beautiful. Thank you, thank you.
太好了，没问题，谢谢
Hey! Hey!
嘿！嘿！
Hey!
嘿！
This part of my life...
我人生的这部分
- Wait! ...this part here...
眼前的这部分
...it' called "Running."
叫做“追赶”
Hey! Hey!
嘿！嘿！
Wait!
等一下！
Hey! Wait!
嘿！等一下！
That was my stolen machine.
那是我被偷的仪器
Unless she was with a guy who sold them too.
除非跟她在一起的那家伙也是做这行的
Which was unlikely...
不过可能性不大
...because I was the only one selling them in the Bay Area.
因为旧金山海湾地区 销售此仪器的仅我一家
I spent our entire life savings on these things.
我把所有的积蓄都押在这上面了
It was such a revolutionary machine.
押在这个革命性的仪器上了
- Can you feel it, baby?    - Oh, yeah.
- 亲爱的，你感觉到了吗？    - 当然了
You got me doing all the work.
你在叫我一个人忙活
What I didn't know is that doctors and hospitals...
但是我没想到，医院的医生们
...would consider them unnecessary luxuries.
会认为它是没用的奢侈品
I even asked the landlord to take a picture.
我甚至请房东给我们照了相
So if I lost one, it was like losing a month' groceries.
所以丢了一台仪器就意味着 损失了一个月的伙食
Hey, hey! Wait! Wait!
嘿！嘿！ 等一下，等一下！
Hey, get back here!
嘿！回来！
Hey, man, l...
嘿，老兄，我…
- Who's he?    - He's that guy...
- 他是谁？    - 就是那个…
- Did you forget?    - Forget what?
- 你忘了吗？    - 忘了什么？
You're not supposed to have any of those.
你不该带这东西回家的
- Yeah, I know.    - You have two now.
- 是的，我知道    - 但你现在却有2台
Hey.
嘿
Hey, Mom.
嘿，妈
One, two, three!
1，2，3
- That's a basketball!    - Hey, hey. What do you mean?
- 是个篮球！    - 嗨，什么意思？
You don't know that that's a basketball.
谁说这是篮球啊？
This could be an ant farm. This could be a microscope or anything.
有可能是“蚂蚁农场” 也可能是显微镜或别的什么
- No, it's not.    - There, there.
- 不，不是的    - 拿不到了吧
All right, come on. Open him up. Open him up.
好吧，快打开吧
- That paper's a little heavy, huh?    - Yeah, but I got it.
- 纸有点厚，是吗？    - 是的，但是我能打开
You should've seen me out there today.
你今天真应该在场的
Somebody stole a scanner. I had to run the old girl down...
有个女孩偷了我的扫描仪 我就一直追她…
Whatever.
随便吧
- What?    - Whatever, Chris.
- 什么？    - 随便怎么着吧，克里斯
What the hell you got attitude about?
你这是什么态度？
- "Whatever" what?    - Every day's got some damn story.
- 随便什么？    - 每天都他妈的有逸闻
Hey, Roy. Roy!
嘿！罗伊！罗伊！
Can you beat your little rug when nobody's out here?
能不能没人的时候再拍毯子？
There's dust and shit all over.
尘土飞扬的
- I'm trying to keep a clean house.    - Hey, wait a second.
- 我只是在打扫房间…    - 嗨，等一下
Look, Linda, relax.
听我说，琳达，放松
We're gonna come out of this. Everything is gonna be fine, all right?
我们会渡过难关的 一切都会好起来的，好吗？
You said that before, when I got pregnant. "lt'll be fine."
你以前就这么说过，我怀孕的时候 你就说：“一切都会好起来的”
- So you don't trust me now?    - Whatever. I don't care.
- 这么说你不再相信我了？    - 随便，我不在乎
- Taxi!    - Mr. Twistle.
- 出租！    - 托斯特尔先生
- Yeah, hi.    - Hi. Chris Gardner.
- 是的    - 你好，我是克里斯・迦纳
Yeah, hi. Listen. What can I do for you?
你好，有什么事吗？
I submitted an application for the intern program about a month ago...
我一个月前交了份实习申请表
...and I would just love to sit with you briefly...
我想找机会和您坐下来简单谈谈…
Listen, I'm going to Noe Valley, Chris.
听着，我要赶去诺亚谷，克里斯
- Take care of yourself.    - Mr. Twistle.
- 你保重    - 托斯特尔先生
Actually, I'm on my way to Noe Valley also.
我正好也要去诺亚谷
How about we share a ride?
我搭个车怎么样？
- All right, get in.    - All right.
- 好吧，上车吧    - 好的
So when I was in the Navy, I worked for a doctor...
我在海军服役时为一个医生工作
...who loved to play golf, hours every day...
他很喜欢高尔夫 每天都要花很多时间在那上面
...and I would actually perform medical procedures...
我还得替他处理医疗事务
...when he'd leave me in the office.
当他不在的时候
So I'm used to being in a position where I have to make decisions and...
我习惯于做出抉择，而且…
Mr. Twistle, listen. This is a very important...
托斯特尔先生，听我说，这很重要
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. This thing's impossible.
对不起，对不起 这东西不可能拼出来的
- I can do it.    - No, you can't. No one can.
- 我可以    - 你不行，没人可以的
- That's bullshit.    - No, I'm pretty sure I can do it.
- 不可能的    - 我确定我能行的
- No, you can't.    - Let me see it.
- 你不行    - 让我看看
Give it here.
给我
Oh, yeah. Oh, wow, you really messed it up.
哦，你真是拼的一团糟啊
Sorry.
不好意思
It looks like it works around a swivel, so the center pieces never move.
看起来这些是围绕一个轴心转动 中间的这部分保持不动
So if it's yellow in the center, that's the yellow side.
所以说如果中间那片是黄色 这面就应该是黄色的
If it's red in the center, that's the red side.
如果中间那片是红色 那么这面就应该是红色的
- Okay.    - So... You can slow down.
- 好的    - 开慢点吧
Listen, we can drive around all day. I don't believe you can do this.
我们可以就这么一直开下去 我就不信你能拼出来
- Yeah, I can.    - No, you can't.
- 我可以的    - 不，你不成
I'm telling you, no one can.
不，你不行，没人可以的
See? That's all I ever do.
看到没？我就只能到这步了
You almost have this side.
那面快拼出来了
Holy cow.
哦，你拼出来了
- You almost had that one.    - I'm gonna get it.
- 哦，那面也快拼出来了    - 我能全部拼出来的
Look at that.
真厉害啊
You're almost there.
快好了
- 17.10.    - This is me.
- 17块1毛    - 我到了
Good job.
拼得不错
- Goodbye.    - Yeah. I'll see you soon.
- 再见    - 回头见
Where are you going, sir?
先生，你要去哪里？
Excuse me, sir. Where are you going, please?
对不起，先生？ 你要去哪里？
Two... A couple of blocks.
呃…2个…几个街区就到
- Just flip around.    - Okay.
- 调下头    - 好的
Hey! Stop it! Hey!
嘿，停下！
- Where are you going? Come here!    - No!
- 你到哪儿去？回来！    -不！
- No, no, no!    - You asshole, give me my money!
- 不，不，不！    - 你这缺德鬼，给我钱
- Give me my money.    - Please stop.
- 给我钱！    - 别，别这样！
- Please, please, please!    - Son of a bitch.
- 别这样！    - 混蛋！
Please! He should've paid you!
他应该付钱，他应该给你钱的！
- Come here!    - I'm sorry.
- 别跑    - 对不起，抱歉
- I'm so sorry.    - I'll kick your ass!
- 对不起    - 我会教训你的！
- I'm sorry!    - Idiot.
- 对不起    - 混蛋！
I'll get you!
我会逮到你的！
I'm going to kill you! I'm going to kill you!
我要宰了你！我要宰了你！
Hey!
嘿！
Stop it, you son of a bitch!
停下！你这个王八蛋！
Stop him!
停下…
The doors are closing.
车门即将关闭
Please stand clear of the doors.
请远离车门
No! No! No!
不，不，不！
No!
不！
- Hello?    - Hey, yeah.
- 喂    - 嗨
Sorry I couldn't make it home on time.
对不起，我没能及时赶回家
- Chris, I missed my shift.    - Yeah, I know. I'm sorry about that.
- 克里斯，我误了班    - 是，我知道，对不起
Look, I'm on my way right now. Are you all right with Christopher?
我现在就在回家路上 你陪着克里斯托弗行吗？
I'm leaving. Chris, I'm leaving.
我要走了，克里斯，我要离开这个家
- What?    - Did you hear what I said?
- 什么？    - 你听到我说的了吗？
I have my things together, and I'm taking our son...
我已经收拾好东西 我要带上儿子
...and we're gonna leave now.
我们现在就走
I'm gonna put the phone down.
我要把电话挂了
- Linda, wait a minute. Hold it, hold...    - I'm going to leave. We are leaving.
- 琳达，等下    - 我们要走了，我们走了
It was right then that I started thinking about Thomas Jefferson...
那一刻，我想起了托马斯・杰斐逊
...the Declaration of Independence...
想起了“独立宣言”
...and the part about our right to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.
想起了其中对生存权，自由权 以及追求幸福权利的描写
And I remember thinking:
我一直在想
How did he know to put the "pursuit" part in there?
他是怎么知道要把“追求幸福” 那部分放进去的？
That maybe happiness is something that we can only pursue.
也许幸福是只能去追求
And maybe we can actually never have it...
但是却永远也追求不到
...no matter what.
无论如何也追求不到的
How did he know that?
他究竟是怎么知道的？
Linda. Linda.
琳达，琳达
- Hello?    - Chris.
- 喂？    - 克里斯吗？
- Who is this?    - Jay Twistle.
- 哪位？    - 杰・托斯特尔
- Hey.    - Dean Witter.
- 嘿    - 迪安・维特公司的
Yeah, of course. How are you?
对…你好吗？
I'm fine. Listen, do you still wanna come in and talk?
我很好，听着，你还想过来聊聊吗？
Yes, sir. Absolutely.
是的，先生，当然了
I'll tell you what. Come on by day after tomorrow, in the morning.
好的，你后天早上来一下
We're interviewing for the internships. You got a pen and paper?
我们要面试实习生，你有纸笔吗？
Yes. Yes, I do.
我有，呃…
- Hold on one second.    - All right.
- 稍等下    - 好的
Hello?
喂
- Chris?    - Go ahead. I have one.
- 克里斯？    - 说吧，我找到了
Write this number down so you can call my secretary, Janice.
记下这个号码，打给我秘书贾尼斯
- She can give you all the specifics.    - Yep.
- 她会告诉你具体事宜的    - 好的
- Okay, 415.    - 415.
- 415    - 415
- 864.    - 864.
- 864    - 864
- 0256.    - 0256.
- 0256    - 0256
- Yeah, extension 4796.    - 4796.
- 对，转4796    - 4796
- Right. Call her tomorrow.    - Yes, sir. 415-864-0256.
- 对，明天就打吧    - 好的，先生，415-846-0256
- Okay, buddy.    - All right, yes.
- 对，兄弟    - 好的，记住了
- Thank you very much.    - We'll see you soon.
- 太感谢你了    - 回头见
864-0256.
864-0256
4796. Janice.
4796，贾尼斯
- Chris.    - Hey.
- 克里斯    - 嗨
Did you...? Have you seen Linda and Christopher?
看到琳达和克里斯托弗了吗？
- No. You catch the game last night?    - No, no.
- 没有，昨晚那场比赛看了没？    - 没，没看
You didn't see that, 118, 1...?
你没看？118，1
Excuse me, did Linda and Christopher come in here?
问一下，琳达和克里斯托弗来过吗？
- No, I haven't see them.    - 119-120. Double overtime.
- 没有，我没看到他们    - 119比120，双加时赛
Moons hits a three-pointer at 17 seconds left.
在还有17秒结束时，投了个三分
Wayne, Wayne, Wayne.
韦恩，韦恩，韦恩
Can't talk to you about numbers right now.
现在不能和你谈数字
- What's your problem with numbers?    - 864-2...
- 为什么？    - 864-2…
- And you owe me money.    - Yeah.
- 你欠我钱    - 没错
You owe me $ 14.
欠我14块
I'm gonna get that to you.
我会给你的
I need my money. I need my money.
给我钱，我需要！
Fourteers a number.
14也是数字啊
Hey, don't you ever take my son away from me again.
嘿，别再把我儿子从我身边带走了！
- You hear me?    - Leave me alone!
- 你听到没？    - 离我远点！
Don't take my son away from me again.
别再把我儿子从我身边带走！
Do you understand what I'm saying to you?
你听到我的话了吗？
Don't you walk away from me when I'm talking to you. Do you hear me?
别就这么走开！我在和你说话呢！ 听到我的话了吗？
- Do you wanna leave?    - Yeah.
- 你想离开吗？    - 没错
- You wanna leave?    - Yes, I want to leave!
- 你想离开吗？    - 是的！我想离开！
Get the hell out of here, then, Linda.
那就快走吧，琳达
Get the hell out of here. Christopher's staying with me.
快滚吧！ 克里斯托弗和我在一起！
You're the one that dragged us down. You hear me?
是你把我们搞成这样的，你听到了没？
- You are so weak.    - No. I am not happy anymore.
- 你太不坚强了！    - 不，我不再幸福
- I'm just not happy!    - Then go get happy, Linda!
- 不再觉得幸福了！    - 那就去找幸福啊，琳达！
Just go get happy.
去找幸福吧！
But Christopher's living with me.
但是克里斯托弗要跟我过！
- Stop!    - Did you hear what I said?
- 闭嘴    - 听到了吗？
Christopher's living with me!
克里斯托弗和我在一起！
Hey. Come on, let's go.
嘿，来，我们走了
- How you doing, Mrs. Chu?    - Hi.
- 你好，朱太太    - 你好
- Where's Mom?    - Look, just get your stuff.
- 妈妈呢？    - 去拿你的东西
But she told me she was coming to pick me up today.
她说今天要来接我的
Yeah, I know.
是，我知道
I talked to Mom earlier. Everything's fine, okay?
我之前和妈妈谈过了 没事的，好吗？
Where do I sleep tonight?
我今晚睡哪儿？
Let me ask you something. Are you happy?
问你个问题 你快乐吗？
- Yeah.    - All right. Because I'm happy.
- 嗯    - 因为我很快乐
And if you're happy and I'm happy, then that's a good thing, right?
如果你快乐，我也快乐 这就是好事，对吗？
- Yeah.    - All right.
- 是的    - 那好
You're sleeping with me.
你今晚和我一起睡
You're staying at home, where you belong, all right?
你待在家里 你本来就该待那儿，好吗？
Christopher.
克里斯托弗
Hey, listen. I need the rent.
嘿，听着，你得交房租
I can't wait anymore.
不能再拖下去了
Yeah, I'm good for that, Charlie. I'm gonna get it.
我会的，查理，我会…
Why don't you go two blocks over at the Mission Inn motel?
你为什么不搬到2个街区外的 祢申汽车旅馆住？
It's half what you pay here.
那比这便宜一半
Listen, Chris. I need you out of here in the morning.
听着，克里斯 我要你明天早上就从这搬走
The hell am I supposed to be out of here tomorrow?
明天就搬走，这怎么可能呢？
I got painters coming in.
油漆工明天要来
- All right, look. I need more time.    - No.
- 好吧，但是再给我点时间    - 不行
All right, I'll paint it myself.
屋子我来刷，好吗？
All right, but I just... I gotta have some more time... I got my son up in here.
再给我点时间，我儿子还在这
All right. One week. And you paint it.
好吧，再给你1周的时间 而且你要粉刷房间
Chris Gardner?
克里斯・迦纳吗？
Yeah. What happened?
是我，什么事？
- Payable to the City of San francisco.    - Does it have to be the full amount?
- 支票抬头写“旧金山市”    - 必须一次性付清吗？
You gotta pay each parking ticket, otherwise, you're staying.
你必须付清每一笔罚单 否则就得待在这儿
This is all I got.
我只有这么多
You verify at 9:30 tomorrow morning.
明早9：30我们会向银行查证的
- What?    - You gotta stay until this thing clears.
- 什么？    - 你得待在这儿直到这事处理完为止
No.
不行
No, I can't spend the night here.
不，我不能在这儿过夜
- I have to pick up my son.    - You verify at 9:30 tomorrow.
- 我还得去接我儿子    - 我们明早9：30向银行查证
Sir, I have a job interview at Dean Witter at 10:15 tomorrow morning.
长官，我明天早上10：15 要去迪安・维特公司面试
- I cannot stay...    - 9:30 tomorrow morning.
- 我不能待在这儿    - 明早9：30
What am I supposed to do with my son?
那我儿子怎么办？我儿子怎么办？
- Is there anyone else who can...?    - I take care of him.
- 还有别人能照顾他吗？    - 我照顾他！
Maybe we can go and have Social Services pick him up.
也许我们可以叫社工去接他
All right. Can I have my phone call, please?
好吧，我能打个电话吗？
- Hello.    - Hey.
- 喂    - 嗨
What do you want?
什么事？
You gotta get Christopher from daycare. I can't.
你得去幼儿园接克里斯托弗 我不能…呃…
Just keep him for the night and I'm... And... Just one night.
就照顾他这一晚上 我…我会…就今天一晚
What happened?
出什么事了？
I'll pick him up from daycare tomorrow.
我明天会去…幼儿园接他
I'm gonna go right... You can just...
我会直接… 你只要…
You can drop him off and I'll pick him up.
你把他送去，我会去接他的
- No.    - Come on, Linda.
- 不行    - 别这样，琳达
- Why you doing that?    - No, I wanna take him to the park.
- 为什么你…    - 不，我想带他去公园…
To Golden Gate after daycare tomorrow.
去金门大桥…明天幼儿园后
- How is he?    - He's fine.
- 他现在怎么样？    - 他很好
All right, just... All right, take him to the park...
好吧，好吧，带他去公园玩吧
...and bring him back, all right?
把他送回来，好吗？
All right, just bring me my son back.
只是…把我儿子送回来
Okay?
好吗？
Linda?
琳达？
I'll bring him back around 6.
我6点左右把他送回来
All right, all right.
好的，好的
Thank you.
谢谢
Bye.
再见
I'm okay?
可以走了吗？
Excuse me. Excuse me.
对不起，借过
Yes, I did.
好的，知道了
Mr. Gardner.
迦纳先生
This way.
这边请
It'll be right this way.
就在那边
What is the word on that one?
那上面是什么？
Chris Gardner.
克里斯・迦纳到了
How are you? Good morning.
你好，早上好
Chris Gardner. Chris Gardner. Good to see you again.
克里斯・迦纳，克里斯・迦纳 又见面了
Chris Gardner. Pleasure.
克里斯・迦纳，见到您很荣幸
I've been sitting there for the last half-hour...
我在外面坐了半个多小时
...trying to come up with a story...
一直想编出个理由
...that would explain my being here dressed like this.
向你们解释我这身打扮出现的原因
And I wanted to come up with a story that would demonstrate qualities...
想编出个故事说明我身上
...that I'm sure you all admire here, like earnestness or diligence.
拥有你们所欣赏的优点… 比如诚实，勤奋
Team-playing, something. And I couldn't think of anything.
团队精神等等 结果我却什么都想不出来
So the truth is...
事实是
...I was arrested for failure to pay parking tickets.
因为没能付清停车罚单 我被拘留了
Parking tickets?
罚单？什么？
And I ran all the way here from the Polk Station, the police station.
我是从警差局… 警察局一路跑来的
What were you doing before you were arrested?
被拘留前你在干什么？
I was painting my apartment.
我在粉刷我的家
Is it dry now?
现在干了吗？
I hope so.
希望如此
Jay says you're pretty determined.
杰说你一心想进我们公司
He's been waiting outside the front of the building...
没错，他拎着个40磅重的玩意儿
...with some 40-pound gizmo for over a month.
在公司门口等了一个多月了
- He said you're smart.    - Well, I like to think so.
- 他说你很聪明    - 我自认是有些
- And you want to learn this business?    - Yes, sir, I wanna learn.
- 你想学这行？    - 是的，先生，我想学
Have you already started learning on your own?
已经开始自学了吗？
Absolutely.
当然
- Jay?    - Yes, sir.
- 杰    - 是的，先生
How many times have you seen Chris?
你见过克里斯多少回？
I don't know. One too many, apparently.
我不清楚 好多次了吧，应该
- Was he ever dressed like this?    - No.
- 他有穿戴成这样吗？    - 不
No. Jacket and tie.
没有，都是西装领带
First in your class in school?
克里斯，你在班上是第一名？
- High school?    - Yes, sir.
- 高中？    - 是的，先生
- How many in the class?    - Twelve.
- 班上一共多少人？    - 12人
It was a small town.
那是个小镇
- I'll say.    - But I was also first in my radar class...
- 我就说嘛    - 我在海军服役时是雷达班的第一名
...in the Navy, and that was a class of 20.
那个班里有20人
Can I say something?
我能说几句吗？
I'm the type of person...
呃…我是这样的人
...if you ask me a question, and I don't know the answer...
如果你问的问题我不知道答案
...I 'm gonna tell you that I don't know.
我会直接告诉你“我不知道”
But I bet you what.
但我向你保证
I know how to find the answer, and I will find the answer.
我知道如何寻找答案 而且我一定会找出答案的
Is that fair enough?
这样可以吗？
Chris.
克里斯
What would you say if a guy walked in for an interview...
如果有个人连衬衫都没穿 就跑来参加面试，你会怎么想？
...and I hired him? What would you say?
如果我最后还雇了这个人，你会怎么想？
He must've had on some really nice pants.
那他穿的裤子一定十分考究
Chris, I don't know how you did it dressed as a garbage man...
克里斯，我难以理解你穿成这样来面试
...but you pulled it off.    - Thank you, Mr. Twistle.
- 但是你刚才的表现很不错    - 谢谢，托斯特尔先生
Hey, now you can call me Jay. We'll talk to you soon.
现在开始叫我杰，回来聊
All right, so I'll let you know, Jay.
好的，我会给你答复的，杰
"You'll let me know, Jay"? What do you mean?
给我答复？什么意思？
Yeah, I'll give you a call tomorrow sometime...
我明天会给你电话的
What are you talking...? You hounded me for this.
你说什么？是你找我的
- You stood here...    - Listen, there's no salary.
- 你当时就站在那里…    - 实习期没有工资
- No.    - I was not aware of that.
- 没有    - 我并不知道没有工资
My circumstances have changed some...
现在我的处境变了
...and I need to be certain that I'll be...    - All right. Okay.
- 我需要确定我能…    - 好的
Tonight.
今晚给我答复
I swear I will fill your spot. I promise.
如果你不把握这机会，我马上给别人
If you back out, you know what I'll look like to the partners?
如果你现在放弃 你知道股东会怎么看我吗？
Yes, an ass... A-hole.
知道，把你看成混蛋
Yeah, an ass A-hole, all the way.
是啊，把我看成混蛋，肯定是的
You are a piece of work.
你还真不简单啊
Tonight.
今晚给我答复
There was no salary.
没有工资
Not even a reasonable promise of a job.
甚至连工作都没有保证
One intern was hired at the end of the program from a pool of 20.
实习结束时，20人中只有1人受雇
And if you werert that guy...
如果受雇的那人不是你的话
...you couldn't even apply the six months' training...
这6个月的培训还不适用于…
...to another brokerage.
其他经纪公司
The only resource I would have for six months...
这6个月里，我的经济来源…
...would be my six scanners, which I could still try to sell.
…就是那6台扫描仪 我还能继续推销那玩意
If I sold them all, maybe we might get by.
如果能全卖掉的话，也许我们能熬过去
- I got him. I got him.    - He's asleep.
- 我来，我来    - 他睡着了
All right.
好吧
Okay, baby.
到了，宝贝
I got it.
我拿着了
I'm going to New York.
我要去纽约了
My sister's boyfriend...
我妹妹的男朋友…
...opened a restaurant, and they may have a job for me there.
…开了家餐厅 可能会给我份工作
So I'm going to New York, Chris.
我要去纽约了，克里斯
Christopher's staying with me.
克里斯托弗和我一起
I'm his mom, you know?
我是他妈妈啊
He should be with his mom.
他应该和他妈妈在一起的
I should have him, right?
他应该和我在一起，对吗？
You know you can't take care of him.
你知道你照顾不了他的
What are you gonna do for money?
那你怎么挣钱？
I had an interview at Dean Witter for an internship...
我去迪安・维特公司参加了个实习面试
...and I got it.
我被录取了
So I'm gonna stand out in my program.
所以我会开始接受培训
Salesman to interrs backwards.
从推销员倒退到实习生？
No, it's not.
不，不是
I gotta go.
我得走了
Tell him I love him, okay?
告诉他我爱他，好吗？
And...
还有…
I know you'll take care of him, Chris.
我知道你会照顾好他的，克里斯
I know that.
我知道的
- Dean Witter.    - Yes, hi.
- 迪安・维特公司    - 你好
Yes, I'd like to leave a message for Mr. Jay Twistle.
呃…我要给杰・托斯特尔先生留言
- Your name?    - Yeah, my name is Chris Gardner.
- 你的名字？    - 我叫克里斯・迦纳
The message is:
留言是:
Thank you very much for inviting me into the program.
非常感谢邀请我参加培训
I really appreciate it and I'd be very pleased to accept your invitation.
真的感谢您 我非常高兴接受您的邀请
Is that all?
就这些吗？
Yes, that's it.
对，就这些
- Okay.    - Thank you.
- 好的    - 谢谢
Bye.
再见
- Be careful with that.    - What?
- 小心点    - 什么？
Be care... Go ahead.
小心…走吧
- Are we there?    - Yep.
- 到了吗？    - 是的
- Hey, you know what today is?    - Yeah.
- 嘿，知道今天周几吗？    - 知道
- What?    - Saturday.
- 周几？    - 周六
- You know what Saturday is, right?    - Yeah.
- 你知道周六要干什么，是吧？    - 知道
- What?    - Basketball.
- 干什么？    - 打篮球
- You wanna go play some basketball?    - Okay.
- 想去打篮球吗?    - 好啊
All right, then we're gonna go sell a bone-density scanner.
好的 之后我们去卖骨质扫描仪，怎么样？
- How about that? Wanna do that?    - No.
- 好吗？    - 不好
Hey, Dad. I'm going pro.
嘿，老爸，我要当职业篮球员
I'm going pro.
我要当职业篮球员
Okay.
哦…呃…
Yeah, I don't know, you know.
这可不好说…
You'll probably be about as good as I was.
你大概会和我以前水平一样糟
That's kind of the way it works, you know. I was below average.
有其父必有其子嘛 我当时篮球就处于平均水平之下
You know, so you'll probably ultimately rank...
所以大概你的最终水平…
...somewhere around there, you know, so...
…也就和我一样，所以…
...I really... You'll excel at a lot of things, just not this.
你在很多方面都很优秀 但是在篮球上不是
I don't want you shooting this ball all day and night.
所以我不希望你就这么 在这整晚的练习投篮
- All right?    - All right.
- 知道了吗？    - 好吧
Okay.
好的
All right, go ahead.
好吧，走吧
Hey.
嗨
Don't ever let somebody tell you...
别让别人告诉你
...you can't do something.
你成不了才
Not even me.
即使是我也不行
- All right?    - All right.
- 知道了吗？    - 知道了
You got a dream...
如果你有梦想的话
...you gotta protect it.
就要去捍卫它
People can't do something themselves...
那些一事无成的人
...they wanna tell you you can't do it.
想告诉你你也成不了大器
If you want something, go get it. Period.
如果你有理想的话，就要去努力实现 就这样
Let's go.
走吧
Dad, why did we move to a motel?
爸，为什么我们要搬到汽车旅馆去？
I told you. Because I'm getting a better job.
跟你说了，因为我会有份更好的工作
- You gotta trust me, all right?    - I trust you.
- 相信我，好吗？    - 我相信你
All right, here. Come on, come on. Keep up.
来，快点，跟上
Dad, whers Mom coming back?
老爸，妈妈什么时候回来？
I don't know, Christopher.
我不知道，克里斯托弗
Dad, listen to this.
爸，你听这个
One day, a man was drowning in the water.
有天，一个人在水里快要淹死了
And a boat came by and said, "Do you need any help?"
这时一只船过来问他“需要帮忙吗？”
He said, "No, thank you. God will save me."
他回答说“不了，谢谢，上帝会救我的”
Then another boat came by. Said, "Do you need any help?"
后来又有一只船过来问“需要帮忙吗？”
And he said, "No, thank you. God will save me."
他说“不用，谢谢了，上帝会救我的”
Then he drowned, and he went to heaven.
后来他淹死了，上了天堂
And he said, "God, why didn't you save me?"
他问“上帝啊，为什么你不救我？”
And God said, "I sent you two big boats, you dummy."
上帝回答说 “我不是派2艘大船去了吗，笨蛋”
Do you like it?
你喜欢吗？
Yeah, that's very funny, man. Give me your hand.
是的，很有意思，过来
- Thank you very much, sir.    - Yes, sir.
- 非常感谢您，先生    - 不客气
- You got the bill of sale here.    - Yes.
- 这是正式的收据    - 好的
All the information you'll need.
和你需要的所有资料
Thank you very much for your business.
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢
One hundred, 200, 20, 40, 45, 46...
100，200 20，40，45，46…
...7, 8, 9, 10.
…7，8，9，10
Thank you.
谢谢
- Hey, you want one of those?    - No, it's okay.
- 嗨，想要那个？    - 不，没事的
Come on, you can have one. Which one?
好吧，可以买一个，要哪种？
- You like that one? How much?    - Twenty-five cents.
- 要这个？多少钱？    - 两毛五
This part of my life is called "Internship."
我人生的这部分叫做“实习”
The 1200 building is Medley Industrial and Sanko Oil.
正前方的是曼尼工业和新科石油
The building across the street is Lee-Ray Shipping.
对街是里瑞运输
In a couple weeks, you'll get call sheets...
几周内你们会拿到一份电话名单…
...from every Fortune 500 company in the financial district.
上面都是金融区财富500强公司员工的电话
You will be pooling from 60 Fortune companies.
你们从中选出60家公司
You will mainly be cold-calling potential clients.
你们主要负责打电话给这些随机选择的潜在客户
But if you have to have lunch with them, have breakfast with them...
必要的话就和他们一起吃饭
...even baby-sit for them, do whatever it takes to familiarize them...
甚至是给他们带孩子竭尽所能向他们介绍
...with our packages. We need you to match their needs and goals...
我们公司提供的各项投资组合根据公司的财务计划
...to one of our many financial plans. In essence, you reel them in...
最大程度的满足客户需求总而言之，你们去钓鱼
...we'll cook the fish.
公司则来烹调
Some of you are here because you know somebody.
你们在座的有些是因为有门路才进来的
Some of you are here because you think you're somebody.
有些人则认为自己是个人物
There's one guy in here who's gonna be somebody.
最终这里只会有一个人真正成为个人物
That persors gonna be the guy...
那就是…能把这个变成这个的人
Eight hundred thousand in commission dollars.
80万美金的佣金
You, you, help me hand these out.
你，你，帮我发一下
This is going to be your bible.
这个将会是你们的“圣经”
You'll eat with it.
你们要吃睡不离身
- You'll drink with it.    - It was simple.
其实道理很简单
X number of calls equals X number of prospects.
打多少电话就意味着有多少机会
X number of prospects equals X number of customers.
有多少机会就意味着有多少客户
X number of customers equals X number of dollars...
有多少客户就意味着有多少钱…
...in the company' pocket.    - Your board exam.
- 进了公司的口袋    - 关于你们的资格考试
Last year, we had an intern score a 96.4 percent on the written exam.
去年我们有个实习生笔试考了96.4％
He wasrt chosen. It's not a simple passlfail.
但是却没被选上，考试不是通过没通过这么简单
It's an evaluation tool we use to separate applicants.
而是我们区分申请者的评估手段
Be safe, score a hundred.
要想保险一点，那就考满分吧
Okay,
好了，我们休息一下，10分钟后继续
-Hey,Mr. Frohm. Chris.    -Hi.
- 嗨，弗雷姆先生，我是克里斯    - 嗨
-Chris,how are you?-I'm good. How you doing?
- 哦，克里斯，你好吗？    - 我很好，你怎么样？
-Fine,thank you for asking.    -First day in there. It was exciting.
- 我很好，谢谢    - 第一天真激动人心啊
You're not quitting on us yet,are you?
你这不是中途落跑吧？
No,sir. Ten-minute break.
不是，先生，只是10分钟的休息时间
Pop out,get a quick bite and then back in there for board prep.
我想随便吃点东西 然后回去准备录用考试
Oh,man,I remember mine.
哦，天啊，我还记得我当年的考试
And ours were only an hour,not three like yours.
不过才1个小时，不像现在3个小时
We didn't do world markets,didn't bother with taxes...
我们那时不考现行市场，也不考税务部分
...and it was still a pain in the ass. Funny what you remember.
但还是令人伤透脑筋 想来好笑，还记得那时…
There was a beautiful girl in that class.
班上有个漂亮女孩…
I can't remember her name,but her face was so...
我记不得名字了，但是她长得…
I've seen an old friend of mine. Do you mind?
我刚看到个老朋友，能失陪一下吗？
-No,go ahead.    -Good talking to you,sir.
- 当然咯，去吧    - 谢谢，跟您聊天很愉快
Hey,asshole. Are you all right,asshole?
嘿，傻x 你还好吧，傻x？
Are you okay?What were you thinking?
你没事吧？ 你在想啥呀？
What are you doing?I could've killed you.
你干嘛呢…我差点就撞死你啦！
I'm trying to cross the street.
我只想过马路
-Well,you're all right?-Yeah,yeah.
- 你没事吧？    - 嗯…嗯
-Where's my shoe?-What?
- 我的鞋呢？    - 什么？
-You knocked off my shoe!-I don't know where your shoe is.
- 你把我的鞋撞丢了！    - 我不知道你的鞋在哪儿！
-Where's my damn shoe?-I don't know.
- 妈的，我的鞋哪儿去了？    - 我不知道
Hey.
嘿
-Did you see it?I lost my shoe.    -No,I'm sorry.
- 你看到了吗？我的鞋丢了    - 没看到，对不起
Hey. Hey,where are you going?
嘿，嘿，你上哪儿去？
-We should wait for the police.    -I gotta go to work.
- 我们应该在这儿等警察    - 我还要回去上班
Hey,you just got hit by a car. Go to the hospital.
你刚被车撞了，快去医院检查一下吧
I'm in a competitive internship at Dean Witter.
我正在迪安.维特实习，忙得很！
Hey,man,you're missing a shoe.
老兄，你少了只鞋
Oh,yeah,thanks. Thank you.
哦，是啊，多谢提醒
Dad.
爸
-You don't have a shoe.    -Yeah,I know.
- 你少了只鞋    - 是啊，我知道
-Wanna know what happened?-Yeah.
- 想知道是怎么回事吗？    - 想啊
I got hit by a car.
我被车撞了
-You got hit by a car?-Yep.
- 什么？被车撞了？    - 是啊
-Where?-Just right by the office.
- 在哪里？    - 就在公司附近
-No,where in your body?-Like,the back of my legs.
- 不是啦，我是问撞到你哪儿了？    - 大腿后面那儿
-Hey,goodbye,Mrs. Chu.    -Goodbye.
- 再见，朱太太    - 再见
-Where you on the street?-Yeah,I was running in the street.
- 在马路上被撞的吗？    - 对，我当时正在马路上跑
Don't do that. You can get hurt.
别再那样了，会被撞伤的
Yeah,thanks.
是啊，谢谢
I'll remember that next time.
下次一定记着
And here I was again.
我又一次…
-Show up early.    -While qualified persons...
- 早早的到了    - 很有条件的人…
...qualified persons are interested in investing and have money to invest.
有条件的人是指那些对投资感兴趣 而且手头有钱去投资的人
-Now,Chris.    -Yes,sir.
- 克里斯    - 是的，先生
Would you get me some coffee,please?
替我拿杯咖啡来，好吗
Favors for Frakesh,our office manager. All day.
给办公室经理弗雷克斯跑腿 从早到晚
My name is Chris Gardner calling for Mr. Michael Anderson.
我是克里斯・迦纳 我找迈克尔・安德森先生
Yes,sir,we're having a lunch actually this Thursday.
是的，先生 提醒您周四约好了共进午餐
Okay,next time. All right,I'm gonna hold you to that.
好吧，那下次好了 好的，不能再爽约哦
Okay,yes,thank you.
好的，没问题，谢谢
Who wants to get me a doughnut?
谁帮我拿个甜甜圈来？
-Chris?-Yes,sir.
- 克里斯？    - 好的，先生
Feeling underrated and unappreciated.
我感到自己被贬低 也没充分得到赏识
Hello,Mr. Ronald fryer.
你好，罗纳德・菲尔先生
Good morning to you,sir. My name is Chris Gardner.
早上好，先生 我叫克里斯・迦纳
I'm calling from Dean Witter.
是迪安・维特公司的
Yes,I have some very,very valuable information on what's called a tax...
是的，我有些非常实惠的资讯 关于节税…
Okay,thank you,sir.
好吧，谢谢，先生
Then catch the bus by 4 to the place where they can't spell "happiness."
然后赶4点的公车，去那个连“幸福” 都不会写的地方接我儿子
Then the cross-town.
再横跨整个城市
The 22 home.
最后坐22路车回家
-Hey,Chris!-Hey. Hi,Ralph.
- 嘿，克里斯    - 嘿，拉尔夫
-I'm waiting.    -All right,I got that for you,Ralph.
- 我还在等房租    - 好的，我会付给你的，拉尔夫
I'm gonna get that for you.
我会付给你的
Whoever brought in the most money after six months was usually hired.
通常情况下，6个月内 为公司揽到最多生意的人将被雇用
Hello,Chris Gardner calling for Mr. Walter Hobb.
你好，我是克里斯・迦纳 我找沃尔特・荷布先生
We were all working our way up call sheets to sign clients.
我们都在各显其能 将电话名单上的人变为我们的客户
-From the bottom to the top.    -Yes,sir.
- 依名单从下往上打电话联系    - 好的
-From the doorman to the CEO.    -Okay.
- 从门卫打到执行长    - 好的
They'd stay till 7,but I had Christopher.
他们都7点下班 但我还要接克里斯托弗
I had to do in six hours what they do in nine.
所以我要在6个小时内 完成他们9个小时做的工作
Good afternoon,my name is Chris Gardner. I'm calling from Dean Witter.
下午好，我是克里斯・迦纳 迪安・维特公司的
In order not to waste any time...
为了节约时间，每通电话之间
...I wasrt hanging up the phone in between calls.
我都直接播打，不放听筒
Okay,thank you very much.
好的，太感谢了
I realized that by not hanging up the phone...
我意识到，这样做
...I gained another eight minutes a day.
我每天可以节约8分钟
Why,good morning to you,my name is Chris Gardner.
早上好，我是克里斯・迦纳
-I'm calling from Dean Witter.    -I wasrt drinking water...
- 迪安・维特公司的    - 而且我也不喝水
...so I didn't ' waste any time in the bathroom.
所以不用浪费时间上厕所
Yes,I'd love to have the opportunity...
是的，我希望有机会…
Okay,no problem at all,sir. Thank you very much.
好的，没问题，先生，谢谢
But even doing all this...
尽管如此
...after two months,I still didn't have time to work my way up a sheet.
2个月后，我连一张名单都没打完
We're feeling really confident about that one as well.
我们在这方面相当的有自信
Walter Ribbor office.
沃尔特・瑞本办公室
Yes,hello,my name is Chris Gardner. I'm calling for Mr. Walter Ribbon.
你好，我是克里斯・迦纳 找沃尔特・瑞本先生
-Concerning?-Yes,ma'am.
- 是关于？    - 是的，女士
I'm calling from Dean Witter.
我是迪安・维特公司的
Just a moment.
请稍等
-Hello?-Mr. Ribbon.
- 你好    - 瑞本先生？
Hello,sir. My name's Chris Gardner. I'm calling from Dean Witter.
您好，先生，我叫克里斯・迦纳 迪安・维特公司的
-Yeah,Chris.    -Yes,Mr. Ribbon...
- 什么事，克里斯？    - 瑞本先生
...I would love to have the opportunity to discuss some of our products.
我希望有机会当面 向您介绍一下我们公司的服务
I'm certain that I could be of some assistance to you.
我肯定能为您做点事
Can you be here in 20 minutes?
你能20分钟内赶过来吗？
-Twenty minutes. Absolutely.    -Just had someone cancel.
- 20分钟，当然了    - 有个预约取消了，你现在就过来吧
I can give you a few minutes before the 49ers.
我会在49人队比赛前给你几分钟时间 （旧金山市橄榄球队）
-Monday Night football,buddy.    -Yes,sir. Thank you very much.
- 老兄，周一晚上可是橄榄球比赛时间啊    - 好的，先生，太感谢您了
-See you soon.    -Bye-bye.
- 那一会儿见    - 再见
Excuse me. Thank you.
感谢您给我这个机会…
-Chris,what's up?-Hey,Mr. Frakesh.
- 克里斯，你好吗？    - 嘿，弗雷克斯先生
Hey,do you have five minutes?
老兄，有5分钟时间吗？
I got a green light from Walter Ribbon...
事实上，沃尔特・瑞本同意我去…
I'm supposed to present commodities to Bromer. Could you move my car?
因为我连一分钟都没，我要给布罗姆 做商品汇报，能帮我停下车吗？
That'd really help me out. It's on Samson,half block,silver Caprice.
那就帮大忙了，车停在萨姆森大街 离这半个街区是辆银色“雪弗莱随想”
Just move it to the other side. They're street sweeping. There's spaces.
只要把车停到马路另一侧就好 那儿刚扫完街，一定有空位
Hang on to these. I have backups in my desk.
钥匙你先拿着 我桌上还有备用的
And you have to jimmy that.
钥匙不太灵光，记得扭一下
-Jimmy what?-You have to jimmy the key.
- 扭一下什么？    - 钥匙不灵光，要扭一下
And the other doors don't unlock. You have to jimmy it.
另一个门锁死了 记得要扭一下
Come on,I'm jimmying it.
快点，我扭着呢
Oh,no!
哦，不要
Come on.
倒是开啊
-Here's the file,Mr. Ribbon.    -Thank you.
- 您要的文件，瑞本先生    - 谢谢
-Thanks a lot.    -Oh,yeah,thanks. Great idea.
- 多谢    - 多谢，这主意很不错
No,no,no!
不，不，不，不！
Rachel,get Ristuccia on the phone for me,please.
瑞秋，替我打个电话找瑞图卡
-Hi.    -Hi.
- 嗨    - 嗨
I'm Chris Gardner. I have an appointment with Mr. Ribbon.
我是克里斯・迦纳 和瑞本先生有个预约
Oh,you just missed him.
噢，他刚走
Thank you.
哦，谢谢
-What's that?-Just filling out a check...
- 你在干什么？    - 我在开支票
...paying some bills...
有些帐单
...and a parking ticket.
停车罚单要付
We don't have a car anymore.
我们没车呀
Yep,I know.
嗯，只是现在没有
I'm gonna need to take you with me this weekend.
我这周周末要带上你
A couple of doctors' offices.
去几个医生的办公室
-On sales calls,okay?-Okay.
- 推销，知道吗？    - 知道了
Then,possibly,we'll go to the football game.
有可能…会带你去看橄榄球赛
-Really?-Possibly.
- 真的？    - 有可能
-All right?-All right.
- 好不好？    - 好吧
Come on,finish up.
快点，快吃完
-Are you sure?-Possibly.
- 真的吗？    - 呵，有可能
Really?
真的？
-Are you bringing it to the game?-Yeah,I don't wanna leave it.
- 你要带这个去看比赛吗？    - 是的，我不想把它丢下
And maybe we're going to the game.
我只说我们可能会去看比赛
-Where are we going now?-To see someone about my job.
- 现在这是去哪儿？    - 去见个工作上的人
I don't understand.
我不明白
-You don't understand what?-Are we going to the game?
- 不明白什么？    - 我们到底去不去看比赛？
I said possibly we're going to the game.
我说了有可能会去
-You know what "possibly" means?-Like probably.
- 知道什么是“有可能”吗？    - 就是“很可能”的意思吧？
No,"probably" means there's a good chance that we're going.
不，“很可能”是说去看比赛的几率很大
"Possibly" means we might,we might not.
“有可能”是说可能去，可能不去
-What does "probably" mean?-It means we have a good chance.
- “很可能”是什么意思？    - 是指可能性很大
And what does "possibly" mean?
那“有可能”呢？
-I know what it means.    -What does it mean?
- 我知道是什么意思！    - 什么意思？
It means that we're not going to the game.
就是我们“不”会去看比赛！
-How did you get so smart?-Because you're smart.
- 你怎么会这么聪明？    - 因为你很聪明
-Are we there?-Yeah.
- 到了吗？    - 是的
-Mr. Ribbon.    -Yes?
- 瑞本先生吗？    - 我就是
How are you,sir?Chris Gardner. Dean Witter.
您好，我是克里斯・迦纳 迪安・维特公司的
-Oh,hi. Hi.    -This is my son,Christopher.
- 哦，嗨，嗨    - 这是我儿子克里斯托弗
-Hi.    -Hey,Christopher.
- 嗨    - 嗨，克里斯托弗
-What are you doing up here?-I came to apologize...
- 有什么事吗？    - 我是为那天…
...for missing our appointment.    -You didn't need to come up.
- 失约而来道歉的    - 没必要专程来的
We were in the neighborhood visiting a very close friend...
我们正好在这附近看一位好朋友
...and I wanted to take this opportunity to say thank you for your time.
我只想借此机会向您表示感谢 多谢您腾出宝贵时间
-I know you probably waited for me.    -Little bit.
- 我知道当时您可能在等我    - 只等了一会儿
I want you to know that I do not take that for granted.
我得说明，我完全没有 “您应该等我”的意思
Oh,come on. What's that?
算了吧，那是什么？
Oh,it's an Osteo National bone-density scanner.
是国骨公司生产的骨质密度扫描仪
A company I bought into prior to going to work at Witter.
是我加入迪安・维特公司之前买进的公司
-I have a meeting after the game.    -You're going to the game?
- 比赛后我有个会    - 你们也去看比赛？
-Yeah.    -Possibly.
- 是的    - 有可能
-Possibly.    -We're going too.
- 有可能    - 我们也要去的
I'm taking my son,Tim. My 12-year-old.
我要带我儿子提姆去，他12岁了
We were just leaving. Tim!
我们要出发了，提姆！
Listen,we'll get out of your way.
那…那我们不耽误您了
Again,thank you very much,and I'm sorry about the other day.
再次感谢您，那天的事很抱歉
And I hope that we can reschedule for later.
希望我们这周晚些时候 能再重新安排个时间会面
-You got it.    -Thank you very much.
- 没问题    - 太谢谢您了，先生
You take care. Here,come on.
多保重，来
-Say bye-bye,Chris.    -Bye.
- 说再见，克里斯托弗    - 再见
Bye,Christopher.
再见，克里斯托弗
Hey,you guys wanna come with us?
想和我们一起去吗？
-What...?To Candlestick?-We're going now. Come with us.
- 呃…去烛台球场吗？    - 我们现在就走，一起去吧
-Where are your seats?-We've... We're upper deck.
- 你们的座位在哪里？    - 我们…我们在顶层露台上
We got a box. Come on.
我们有个包厢，来吧
-You wanna sit in the box?-No.
- 你想坐包厢吗？    - 不…想
It's not actually a box. It's,you know,a private section.
呵呵，不是说真的箱子啦 是个球场的专属区
It's more comfortable. You wanna go?
看比赛更舒适些，想去吗？
-Okay.    -Okay,kids in the back.
- 好啊    - 好了，孩子们坐后排
Hey,why don't you just put that in your car?
嘿，何不把那东西留在你车里
-Yeah,okay. Sure,sure.    -We don't have a car.
- 呃…好…好啊…好啊    - 我们没车
-Oh,my...    -What happened?
- 啊…噢…我的…    - 怎么了？
I think I got stung by a bee.
大概被蜜蜂蜇了
-You all right?-Oh,yeah. Goodness. I'm fine.
- 还好吗？    - 是的，我很好，没事
-You're not allergic or anything?-No,no,no.
- 你对这个不过敏吧？    - 不，不，不
-Where'd he get you?-Just right at the back of my head.
- 蜇到哪儿了？    - 头后面
-Are you okay?-Yeah,I'm fine,Christopher.
- 没事吧？    - 是的，没事，克里斯托弗
-Does it hurt?-Christopher,I'm fine.
- 痛吗？    - 克里斯托弗，我没事
-Let me see.    -Christopher,sit back. Sit back.
- 让我看看    - 克里斯托弗，坐好，坐好
Thomas Jefferson mentions happiness a couple times...
托马斯・杰斐逊在“独立宣言”中 几次提及“幸福”这个词
May seem like a strange word to be in that document...
这个词出现在“独立宣言”中 似乎有些怪异
...but he was sort of... He was an artist.
但是他似乎是… 是个艺术家
He called the English "the disturbers of our harmony."
他称英国人为“破坏我们和谐的人”
And I remember standing there that day...
我还记得那天站在那里
...thinking about the disturbers of mine.
思考着“破坏我和谐的人”
Questions I had: Whether all this was good.
我的疑问是…我做这一切是好是坏？
Whether I'd make it.
我究竟能否成功
And Walter Ribbon and his Pacific Bell pension money...
沃尔特・瑞本和他所管理的数百万 “太平洋贝尔电话公司”退休金资产
Yeah!
好！
It was a way to another place.
是让我晋升的好途径
Wow,this is...
哇，这…呃…
This is the way to watch a football game here.
这才叫看球
-Thank you very much for this,really.    -Hey,it's my pleasure,Chris.
- 真的谢谢您    - 别客气，克里斯
And,Mr. Ribbon,I also wanna thank you for giving me the opportunity...
瑞本先生，还要感谢您给我个机会
...to discuss the asset management capabilities of Dean Witter...
向您介绍我们公司在资产管理方面的能力
...which we believe to be far superior...
相信我们的能力会比
...to anything you got going over at Morgan Stanley.
摩根史坦利公司更为卓越
Really,I think you're gonna be blown away.
真的，相信您一定会很惊讶
Point blank,Dean Witter needs to be managing your retirement portfolio.
坦白说，迪安・维特公司 该替您管理退休金的投资运用
You know,I didn't have any notion that you were new there.
克里斯，我不知道你是那里的新员工
I like you,but there's not a chance I'm gonna let you direct our fund.
我很欣赏你，但是我绝不可能 叫你来管理我们的资金
That's just not gonna happen anytime soon,buddy.
至少近期之内不可能，老兄
So,you know,come on,relax. Let's play the game. Go,go,go!
所以…轻松点，看球吧 快，快
Yes!
好呀！
-Here you go.    -All right.
- 给你(名片)    - 好的
I've had a few ideas already,absolutely.
我己替你想好几个方案了
-Chris,I'll talk to you later.    -I'm gonna give you a call.
- 克里斯，回头和你再聊    - 我肯定会给你打电话的
Nice to meet you,Chris. Give me a call.
很高兴认识你，给我电话
Yes,absolutely. Thank you.
当然，谢谢
-Bye.    -Bye,Christopher.
- 再见    - 再见，克里斯托弗
After four months,we had sold all our scanners.
4个月后，我们卖掉了所有的扫描仪
It seemed we were making it.
看来我们在向成功迈进了
What's the...
- 世界上最快的动物是什么？    - 长耳兔
It seemed we were doing good.
看来我们…做的还不错
Till one day...
直到有一天
...that day...
那天…
...that letter brought me back to earth.
一封信又把我带回了现实
This part of my life is called "Paying Taxes."
我人生的这部分 叫做“付税”
If you didn't pay them...
如果你不付…
...the government could stick their hands into your bank account...
政府就会把手伸向你的银行户头 [没收金额：$600]
...and take your money.
强行拿走你的钱
Dad.
老爸
No warning. Nothing.
事先没有任何警告 什么都没有
It can't be too late. That's my money.
不会太迟的，那是我的钱
How is somebody just gonna just take my money?
怎么能就这么拿走我的钱呢？
I was... I was...
我…我…
Listen,l... That's all the money that I have.
听着 我…那是我全部积蓄
You cannot go into my bank acc... No...
你们不能…从我帐户里…不…
It was the 25th of September.
那天是9月25日
I remember that day.
我记得那天
Because that' the day that I found out...
因为就在那天我发现
...there was only 21 dollars and 33 cents left in my bank account.
我的银行帐户只剩下$21.33
I was broke.
我破产了
-Dressed yet?-No.
- 穿好衣服了吗？    - 没呢
Chris!Chris!Don't jerk me around,okay,Chris?
克里斯，克里斯，别耍我，克里斯？
I'm not jerking you around,Ralph,all right?I'm gonna get it.
我没有，拉尔夫 我会给你，会付钱给你的
-I need that money now,not later.    -When I get it,you get it,Ralph.
- 我要房费，现在就要！不是以后！    - 我有了钱马上就付给你，拉尔夫
Now!
我现在就要！
Hey,what's happening,man?
- 嘿    - 嘿，克里斯
Wayne,I need to get that $ 14 from you.
韦恩，还我那14块
I thought I didn't owe you that now.
我以为不欠你了
-What?Why?-Why what?
- 什么？为什么？    - 什么为什么？
Why would you think you don't owe me my money?
为什么你觉得不欠我钱了？
I helped you move.
不是帮你搬家了吗？
You drove me two blocks,Wayne.
你开车送了我2个街区，韦恩
That's 200 yards.
也就200码
It's been four months,Wayne.
都4个月了，韦恩
I need my money. I need my money. I need my money right now.
我需要那钱，我要我的钱 现在就要！
-I don't have it,man. I'm sorry.    -Go get my money.
- 我没有钱    - 韦恩，把钱还我
-Wayne,get my mo...    -I really don't,man. It's $ 14.
- 把钱给我    - 我真的没有，老兄，才14块
It's my $ 14!Go get my money!
那是我的14块！把钱给我！
-All of this for $ 14.    -Get my money,Wayne.
- 就14块    - 给我钱，韦恩！
Dad,look at me!
老爸，看我！
Dad.
老爸！
-Should I go?-Sure,man. Why not?
- 要滑下去吗？    - 当然，滑下来吧
-Stay here.    -Dad,look.
- 待在那儿，克里斯托弗    - 老爸，快看
-No,no. Stay right here.    -Dad.
- 不，不，待在那儿    - 老爸
Did you hear what I said?Did you hear me?
听到我说什么了吗？听到了吗？
-Dad,where you going?-Hey,what did I say?
- 老爸，你要去哪？    - 待在那儿！
Dad!
爸
Dad,wait!Dad!
老爸，等一下
-Dad.    -I gotta...
- 老爸！    - 我得…
I gotta get back to the '60s,man. That's what I wanna do.
我得回到60年代去，老兄 我就想这么做
When I was younger. I wanna see Jimi Hendrix do that guitar on fire.
我年轻的时候 我要看吉米.汉卓克表演激情吉他！
Bring back my time machine!
把时光机拿回来！
Bring my time machine back!
把时光机给我拿回来！
-Dad,where are we going?-Just be quiet.
- 爸，我们要去哪里？    - 别说话
Go get your things. Go.
去，拿上你的东西，去！
-Chris?-Yes.
- 克里斯吗？    - 是的
Dr. Telm can't get back to meet you. I'm sorry.
特尔医生现在没法回来见你，抱歉
Where are we going now?
我们现在去哪？
Gotta... We gotta see somebody else.
还得…还得去见别人
I'm tired.
我累了
I know.
我知道
Doesrt seem to be functioning right now.
好像仪器不太工作
-I have to go now,Chris.    -No,no,no.
- 我得走了，克里斯    - 不，不，不
Just give me a second. I'm sure I'm gonna be able to figure it out.
给我点时间，我能找出问题所在
Chris. Chris,just come back when it's working.
克里斯，克里斯，弄好以后再来吧
-No,no. I have to fix it now.    -No.
- 不，不，我现在就能把它修好    - 不是的
Look,I'll still be putting money in the office,then,all right?
听着，这仪器我还是会买的，好吗？
I really have to go,Chris.
我真的要走了，克里斯
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢，多谢
Thank you for your time. I appreciate it.
谢谢你花时间 我很感激
I'll see you soon.
下回见
Why are our things here?
为什么我们的东西在这里？
Dad.
老爸
-Let's go. Come on.    -Where?
- 我们走吧，快点    - 去哪？
-Just out of here.    -Why?
- 只是…离开这里    - 为什么？
-We can't stay here tonight.    -Yes,we can. Open the door!
- 我们今晚不能住这儿    - 可以的，把门打开！
-Did you hear what I said?Let's go.    -Open the door!
- 你听到我的话了吗？快走    - 开门！
Hey,did you hear what I said?Stop it.
嗨，没听见我说什么了吗？ 停下来！
Stop it.
别吵！
Come on.
走啊
Wayne!
韦恩！
Get up. Stand up. Come on.
起来，站起来
Where are we going?
我们去哪？
-Dad,where are we going?-I don't know.
- 爸，我们去哪里？    - 我不知道
It's not a time machine.
这不是时光机
Dad.
爸
The guy said it was a time machine. It's not a time machine. He was wrong.
那个说它是时光机的家伙 这不是时光机，他错了
-What guy?-The guy. He was at the park.
- 哪个家伙？    - 在公园里的那人
He said it was a time machine.
他说这是时光机
Yes,it is.
没错，这是时光机
No,it's not.
不，不是
-It is.    -No,it's not.
- 是的    - 不是
All we gotta do is push this black button right here.
我们只需要按一下 这里的这个黑色按钮
Wanna push it?
想按吗？
Okay.
好吧
Come on.
过来吧
Come on,man.
来吧，小伙子
Right here.
按这里
Wait a minute. Where you wanna go?
等一下，你想去哪里？
I don't know. Some place from before.
我不知道，远古的什么地方
You gotta close your eyes.
闭上眼睛
You close your eyes. I wanna see.
你闭上眼睛，我还想看呢
All right,come on. We'll push it together.
好吧，我们一起来按
You gotta close your eyes. Close your eyes.
闭上眼睛，快闭上眼睛
It takes a few seconds.
几秒钟就好
Oh,my goodness.
哦，天啊
Open,open,open!
睁开，睁开，快睁开眼睛！
-What is it?-Dinosaurs.
- 是什么啊？    - 恐龙！
-Where?-You don't see all these dinosaurs?
- 在哪里？    - 你看不到这些恐龙吗？
Look around. Look at all these dinosaurs.
看看四周，看看这些恐龙
-Can you see them?-Yeah.
- 你看到了没？    - 看到了
Wait. Come on,come on.
快点，快点，快点！
-Wait,watch out.    -What is it?
- 等一下，当心！    - 怎么了？
Don't step in the fire. We're cavemen.
别把火踩灭了，我们是山顶洞人
We need this fire,because there's no electricity...
我们需要这些火种取暖 因为我们没有电
...and it's cold out here,okay?
这里又很冷，知道吗
-Watch out!-Whoa!Oh,my good... A T. Rex.
- 当心，当心    - 哦，天啊，霸王龙！
Get your stuff. Get your stuff. Get it.
快收拾好东西，收拾好东西，快点
-We gotta find someplace safe.    -Like what?
- 我们得找个安全的地方    - 比如呢？
We need a cave.
找个山洞
A cave?
山洞？
-We gotta find a cave. Come on.    -Okay.
- 我们需要找个山洞，快点    - 好吧
Come on,come on.
快点，快点
Watch your back!Look out.
小心背后！当心
Here it is. Here's a cave. Come on.
这有个山洞，快过来
Right here,right here. Go,go,go.
就在这，就在这 快进去，快点
Go ahead. Get in.
进去，快进去
Hurry,hurry,hurry.
快点
-Are we safe?-Yeah,I think so.
- 我们安全了吗？    - 是的，我想是的
Hey.
嘿
-How you doing,Jay?-I'm doing good.
- 你好吗？    - 我很好
How are you getting along?
你怎么样？
-Good. I'm good.    -You doing good?
- 很好，我很好    - 你过的还好？
-How you doing?-I'm doing great.
- 你怎么样？    - 我很好
Where you going?
你这是去哪儿？
L... Sacramento.
萨克拉门托（加州首府）
Because I'm trying to move a couple guys from...
我正想办法把几个人…
They're at PacBell,and I'm trying to bring them over...
几个“太平洋贝尔”的人… 把他们弄过来…
Get them over to us.
成为我们的客户
So they got me going out there golfing.
我得过去和他们打高尔夫
Awesome.
不赖啊
Hey,let them win a round.
把他们争取过来
Deborah,someone's asking for you.
黛布拉，有人找你
-Where?-He's outside. Please come with me.
- 在哪里？    - 他在外面，请跟我来
Hi.
嗨
-Can I ask you a question?-Sure.
- 能问您点事吗？    - 当然
We need a room.
我们需要个住的地方
Just until I can fix this and sell it.
直到我把这个修好并卖掉
-There's just some glass work.    -Let me stop you right there.
- 只是修理些镜片    - 先生，先停一下
-I wish I could help you...    -This is my son,Christopher.
- 我很希望能帮你，但是…    - 这是我儿子，克里斯托弗
-He's 5 years old.    -Hi,baby.
- 他5岁    - 你好，孩子
-We need some place to stay.    -Okay,and I would love to help you...
- 我们需要一个住的地方    - 好的，我很想帮助你们
...but we don't take men here. It's only women and children.
但我们不收留男士，只收留妇女儿童
He can stay here,but you have to find someplace else to go.
他待在这里可以，但是你得另找住处
We gotta stay together.
我们不能分开
We got... We're...
我们…我们…
-Okay,listen.    -You gotta have some place...
- 好的，好的，听着…    - 你们一定有什么地方…
Try Glide Memorial. The building books up at 5.
你试试格莱德纪念教会收容所 那儿5点关门
So you hurry up. There's a line.
你得快点去，很多人排队
-And where is it?Come on.    -Ellis and Jones.
- 在哪里？ 我们走    - 艾莉斯和琼斯街交口
Hey,everybody. We have four spots left,and that's all.
嘿，大家听好，只剩下4个位子了 只有4个了
-Man.    -Hey,come on,man.
- 嘿，老兄，别这样    - 别这样
-Come on.    -Come on,what?
- 别这样    - 别哪样？
-Hey,that's my spot.    -Back off.
- 那是我的位子    - 滚开
Come on,don't do this to me. Don't...
- 别这样，别    - 一边儿去
Dad!
老爸！
Stop it!Break it up!Break it up!
住手，把他们拉开
Stop!Stop!
住手，住手！
Get out of the line,both of you. Both of you.
走，你们两个都走
I was here first. They told me that we had to be on time.
我先来的，是我先来的 他们告诉我要准时来
I got here on time. I was in line.
我是准时来的，就在队里排着
I came from work,I got my son.
我下了班，接了我儿子
I was here on time. We were here on time!
我是准时到这的！ 我们准时到的！
He sliced in front of him in line.
他趁他不注意插队的
-Who did?-He did.
- 谁？    - 他
Come on,come on,Rodney. Come on. Let's go. Get out of line.
走吧，走吧，罗尼 走吧，别排队了
That's it. No more.
就这样了，没位子了
-What's your favorite color?-Green.
- 你最喜欢什么颜色？    - 绿色
Green?
绿色？
-What do you like that's green?-Trees.
- 喜欢什么绿色的东西？    - 树木
Trees. What else?
树木，还有呢？
Holly.
冬青树
-Holly. What's holly?-The Christmas stuff.
- 冬青树？什么冬青树？    - 圣诞节装饰用的
Christmas stuff.
啊，圣诞装饰
What's that?
怎么了？
I guess they want us to go to sleep.
大概我们该睡觉了
Here you go. We gotta make sure Captain America's warm in there.
好了，我们不能叫“美国英雄”冻着
Can you breathe?
他能呼吸吗？
-You're good?-Yeah.
- 他还好吧？    - 是的
-I gotta go work on the scanner...    -Don't go.
- 好了，我得去修扫描仪…    - 别走
No,no,no. I'm gonna be right outside the door.
我不走，不走，我就在门口
All right?I'm just gonna be right there. I'll leave the door open a little bit.
好吗？我就在外面，把门开着一点
And I'll be able to hear you if you call me.
这样你叫我，我就能听到
I wanna go home.
我想回家
But that's why I gotta work on the scanner.
所以我才更得修好扫描仪啊
All right?
好吗？
I'm gonna go out there.
我就在外面
I'm gonna leave the door open. I'll be right up the stairs.
把门敞开点 我就在楼梯那儿
I'll be able to hear you if you call me.
要是你叫我，我肯定能听到的
-All right?-All right.
- 好吗？    - 好的
You gotta trust me,okay?
你要相信我，好吗？
You gotta trust me.
你得相信我
I trust you. I trust you.
我相信你，我相信你
I trust you.
我相信你
-I can't hear you.    -I trust you. I trust you.
- 我听不到啊    - 我相信你
Give me a kiss.
亲亲
-I'll just be a little while,okay?-All right.
- 我一会就回来，好吗？    - 好的
-I'll be right here.    -Okay.
- 我就在这儿    - 知道
-Can you still hear me?-Yeah.
- 听得到我吗？    - 听得到
-Can you hear me?-Yeah.
- 能听到我吗？    - 能
-Do you trust me?-Yeah.
- 你相信我吗？    - 相信
-Yeah.    -Like that?
- 好的    - 像这样？
-Yeah,put that...    -Then you go like that.
- 对，放进…    - 然后…
-Is that okay?-I don't know. What do you think?
- 这样行吗？    - 我不知道，你觉得怎么样？
Good.
那好
Let's go. Get your stuff.
我们走吧，把你的东西拿上
-Hey,why don't you leave it?-We can't.
- 为什么不把它放在这儿？    - 不行
We're gonna have a different room later.
我们今晚住别的房间
Go.
走吧
Hey,Chris.
嘿，克里斯
-Hey,good morning,Mr. Frakesh.    -What's up?
- 嗨，早上好，弗雷克斯先生    - 这是怎么了？
Work trip.
出公差
Your wife,Martha,works at PacBell also,correct?
你太太也在“太平洋贝尔”工作吧？
-Yes,she does.    -And you guys are both...
- 是的    - 你们两个…
...Iooking to retire at the same time?
你们两个想同时退休吧？
We'd like to retire and maintain our lifestyle...
我们希望退休后不要因为过重的税务
...without paying a lot of taxes.
而改变现有的生活方式
So basically,you want nobody's hands in your pockets but your own?
也就是说，除了你自己 不想让别人的手伸进你口袋
Are you familiar with tax-free municipal...
听过免税国债券…
I learned to finish my work quickly.
我学会了尽快完成工作
I had to finish quickly.
我不得不快点…
To get in line at Glide by 5.
好在5点钟赶去格莱德排队
Come on.
快点
Hold that bus!Hold the bus!
等等，等我们一下
My Captain America!
我的“美国英雄”
Dad!Dad!Dad!
爸，等一下
Stop it!Shut up!Shut up!
住嘴，住嘴
-Why don't you let the lady in?-Hey,back up.
- 为什么不让女士先上？    - 走开
-Hey,man,that's not cool.    -Back up!Back up!
- 老兄，这样可不对    - 滚开，退后，一边儿去！
Come on.
来吧
Dad,we need to get it!
老爸，我们得捡回“美国英雄”…
The important thing about that freedom train...
重要的是自由列车之行
...is it' got to climb mountains.
就如同翻山越岭
We all have to deal with mountains.
我们都得面对险山砾石
You know,mountains that go way up high.
山，有险峻也有低谷
-Amen,preacher!-Yes.
没错
We know what those mountains are,here at Glide.
我们知道生活中的那些险峻是什么 在这，在格莱德
We sing about them.
我们用歌声来歌唱他们
Lord,don't move that mountain
# 上帝，别让险峻离开
Give me strength to climb it
# 赐予吾翻越攀登之力
Please don't move That stumbling block
# 请别挪开吾足下之绊脚石
But lead me,Lord,around it
# 指引吾前进的方向
My burdens,they get so heavy
# 重担虽负于肩
Seems hard to bear
# 痛苦难以忍受
But I won't give up No,no
# 吾不会也不曾放弃
Because you promised me
# 只因吾等之间的承诺
You'd meet me at the altar of prayer
# 那日二人在祭坛相…遇
-Lord don't move that mountain    -Please don't move that mountain
# 上帝，别让险峻离开 # 请别让险峻离开
But give me strength to climb it
# 但请赐予吾翻越攀登之力
Whers your test?
考试是什么时候？
Tomorrow.
明天
Are you ready?
你准备好了吗？
Of course.
当然了
Thank you,sir.
谢谢您，先生
-Hey. How you doing?-Hey.
- 嘿    - 嘿，你好
So did you finish the whole thing,or you have to go somewhere...
你都答完了吗？ 还是要去什么地方？
I have to go somewhere.
我赶着去个地方
-But I finished the whole thing too.    -Oh,good.
- 但是我也都答完了    - 不错啊
-You?-Yeah.
- 你呢？    - 我也都答完了
-How'd you feel about the graphs?-Easy.
- 那些图表题你感觉怎么样？    - 太容易了
I struggled with the essay question on the back. What did you write?
试卷背后那道论述题难住我了 你怎么答的？
-Essay question?-Yeah,on the back.
- 论述题？    - 是啊，在背面
Hey,Chris.
嗨，克里斯
-Hey. Jeff,right?49ers game.    -Yeah.
嗨，杰夫，对吗？ 49人队那场比赛见过？
-Yeah,you were gonna give me a call?-I never actually got your number.
- 没错，什么时候给我打电话？    - 我一直都没有你电话
Here's my number. Call me,okay?
这是我的电话，给我打电话，好吗？
Yes,sir. Absolutely. Thank you very much.
好的，当然了，谢谢
Chris,you got five bucks?I left my wallet upstairs.
克里斯，有5块钱吗？ 我把钱包落在楼上了
Let me run up and grab that for you,Mr. Frohm.
我现在到楼上帮您拿下来，弗雷姆先生
No,I gotta be at CAL Bank at 4,and I'm late.
不了，我得在4点前赶去加州银行 我要晚了
-I'll pay you back,honest.    -Five is good?
- 我会还你的，真的    - 5块钱够吗？
Five is lovely. Thank you. Thank you.
足够了，谢谢
That's it. That's the room quota.
好了，就这么些床位配额
There's no more space. You gotta head out.
再没有多余的位子了，到别处去找吧
That's it for today. Come back tomorrow.
今天没有位子了 明天再来吧
All the rooms are full. It's completely full.
没有床位了，全满了…
That's it. Just keep heading out. Come back tomorrow.
就这样，保持秩序 明天再来吧
You like it?
好吃吗？
Twenty. One,two,three,four.
20，21，22，23，24
Now,here's your bulb,and there's your ferrite core inductor.
这是你要的灯泡 还有圈型适配器
-How much?-Eight dollars.
- 多少钱？    - 8块
-What's that?-It's to repair the light.
- 那是什么？    - 修灯用的
Can I see it?
我看看行吗？
Yeah,sure. Just don't break it.
好的，别弄坏了…
Unless you wanna sleep in a room with me for the rest of your life.
除非你下半辈子都想和我挤一个房间
I don't mind.
我不介意
Yeah,you will.
你会的
Why don't you get some sleep,okay?
好好睡一觉，好吗？
Okay.
好的
-Warm enough?-Yeah.
- 够暖和吗？    - 是的
Did Mom leave because of me?
是因为我妈妈才离开的吗？
-What?-Did Mom leave because of me?
- 什么？    - 妈妈是因为我才走的吗？
Don't... Don't even think something like that.
别…千万别这么想！
Mom left because of Mom.
妈妈走了是因为她自己的原因
And you didn't have anything to do with that,okay?
和你没关系，知道了吗？
Okay.
知道了
You're a good papa.
你是个好爸爸
All right,go to sleep.
好了，睡觉吧
-I love you.    -I love you too.
- 我爱你    - 我也爱你
So far,so good,Chris.
还不错啊，克里斯
-It works.    -Thank you very much.
- 工作了    - 太谢谢你了
Two hundred and fifty dollars. Four more weeks of oxygen.
250美元 4周的生活开支
One hundred,20,40,60,80,200.
120，140，160，180，200
Twenty,30,40,50.
220，230，240，250
-Anything else?-No,sir.
- 还需要别的吗？    - 不了，谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
多谢，多谢
-You ready?-Yep.
- 好了吗？    - 嗯
-Are we going to the church place?-No.
- 我们是要去教堂那儿排队吗？    - 不是
Where are we going,then?
那去哪里？
-Probably stay at a hotel.    -A hotel?
- 去旅馆    - 旅馆？
Just for the night.
就今天一晚上
We can go back to the cave if you like.
你要是愿意的话 我们可以回那个山洞去住
No,thank you.
不用了，谢谢
-Ever?-I hope not.
- 永远不回去了？    - 希望不会
Why not?
为什么不？
Well,because some things are fun the first time you do them...
因为有些事情第一次做兴致昂然 之后再重复就索然无趣了
-Like the bus?-Yeah,like the bus.
- 就象坐公车一样？    - 对，就像坐公车
I'm sorry,I shouldn't laugh,should I?
对不起，我不该笑的，对吗？
Sometimes when we're moving at night...
有时我们穿梭与夜色下…
...we pass houses with lights and people.
在人与房屋之间穿行
Sometimes you can hear them laugh.
有时你能听见他们的笑声
The next day,after work...
第二天
...we just went to the beach.
下班后，我们去了海边
Far away from anything.
远离一切
Everything.
远离所有尘嚣
Just Christopher and me.
只有克里斯托弗和我两个人
-Did you see me?-Yeah.
- 看到我了吗？    - 看到了
Far away from buses and noise...
远离公车，噪音…
...and a constant disappointment in my ten-gallon head...
而我“无敌大头”里充斥不断的失望
...and myself.
远离自我
-Chris,thank you very much.    -Well,thank you,Dean.
- 谢谢你，克里斯    - 谢谢，迪安
-Take care.    -You made all the right moves.
- 保重    - 你的选择很明智
Thanks,Chris.
谢谢，克里斯
Because when I was young...
我小时候
...and I'd get an A on a history test or whatever...
历史还是什么考了个甲
...I'd get this good feeling about all the things that I could be.
当时我有种能成为任何栋梁之才的感觉
And then I never became any of them.
但结果却什么也没成
-Hey,Chris.    -Hey.
- 嗨，克里斯    - 嗨
-How you doing,Jay?-I'm doing fine.
- 杰，你好吗？    - 我很好
Rumor has it you signed 31 accounts for us from Pacific Bell.
有传闻说你从“太平洋贝尔”那儿 签了31个客户过来
Yeah,yeah.
是啊
Met some guys at a ball game,got some cards. I've been working.
我在球场上认识了些人，拿了名片 正在争取他们
I guess.
我想也是
So one more day.
我说…再一天就结业了
Getting nervous?
紧张吗？
-No,I'm okay.    -Yeah?
- 还好    - 是吗
Listen,whatever happens...
听着，无论结果如何
...you've done a fantastic job,Chris.
你的实习非常出色，克里斯
I mean that.
这是我的真心话
Take care of yourself.
保重
Yes,Mr. Johnson. Chris Gardner,Dean Witter.
约翰森先生 克里斯・迦纳，迪安・维特公司的
Yes,sir. Just calling to thank you very much...
我是特意打电话来感谢
...for your support at last month's seminar.
您上回研讨会上对我的支持
Yes,sir. Absolutely.
是的，先生，当然了
Yes,sir.
是的，先生
No,sir,that's it.
没有了，就这些
Thank you very much. Bye-bye.
非常感谢，再见
Chris. Come.
克里斯，来
-Hi,Chris.    -Mr. Frohm,good to see you.
- 嗨，克里斯    - 弗雷姆先生，见到您很高兴
-Nice shirt.    -Thank you,sir.
- 衬衫很漂亮    - 谢谢
-Chris.    -Hey,Jay.
- 克里斯    - 你好，杰
-Chris.    -Chris,sit down,please.
- 克里斯    - 克里斯，请坐
I thought I'd wear a shirt today.
我觉得…今天应该穿衬衫来…
You know,being the last day and all.
最后一天了
Well,thank you. Thank you. We appreciate that.
谢谢，很感谢
But...
但是…
...wear one tomorrow though,okay?
明天接着穿，好吗？
Because tomorrow's going to be your first day...
因为明天将是你的第一天…
...if you'd like to work here as a broker.
如果你想在这里做经纪人的话
Would you like that,Chris?
你愿意吗，克里斯？
Yes,sir.
是的，先生
Good. We couldn't be happier.
好极了，我们太高兴了
So welcome.
那么…欢迎你
-Was it as easy as it looked?-No,sir. No,sir,it wasrt.
- 并不象看上去的那么容易吧？    - 当然不是，先生
-Good luck,Chris.    -Thank you. Thank you.
- 祝你好运，克里斯    - 谢谢，谢谢
Oh,Chris.
哦，克里斯
I almost forgot.
我差点忘了
Thank you.
谢谢
This part of my life...
我人生的这部分
...this little part...
这个小阶段
...is called "Happiness."
叫做“幸福”
Christopher. Christopher. Come here.
克里斯托弗，过来
So how many...
那…一共有…
...planets are there?
一共有多少行星？
-Seven.    -Seven?
- 7颗    - 7颗？
Nine.
9颗
Who's the king of the jungle?
丛林之王是谁？
-Gorilla.    -The gorilla?
- 猩猩    - 猩猩？
The gorilla?
猩猩？
No. Lion.
不对，是狮子
Oh,yeah. Lion,lion,lion.
对啊，是狮子，狮子，狮子
Hey,Dad,listen to this. Knock,knock.
嘿，爸，听这个，叩！叩！
-Who's there?-Shelby.
- 谁啊？    - 谢尔碧
Shelby who?
哪个谢尔碧？
Shelby coming around the mountain When she comes
当她来的时候谢尔碧正从山里走来
-Knock knock.    -Who's there?
- 叩！叩！    - 谁啊？
-Nobody.    -Nobody who?
- 没人    - 谁是没人？
Nobody who?
谁是没人？
Now,that's funny. I like that one.
哦～ 哈哈，好笑，这个我喜欢